the fairchild Republic a ten Lightning bolt or simply the
疣猪is one of the most iconic planes in the us air
force
a plane developed in the middle of the cold war
with a specific type of warfare in mind
if the cold war turned hot
one area was destined to become a battleground
a fifty kilometer corridor of Lowland valleys called the
Fulda gap where any invading troops would be channeled on
their March from east Germany to west Germany
it was the shortest route to France  Frankfurt
and the strategically important Rhine river
if war broke out
this corridor would be a vital region to secure
and each side of the folda gap was
defended by armored divisions
to cope with this threat environment
the us developed an operational
doctrine called airland battle
and the a ten was developed as a vital component of
this strategy a low flying tank killer which would
work closely with the troops on the ground to break up
enemy formations at the front while high flying
bombers harassed the supply lines at the rear
the a ten was a plane designed
specifically for the role of close air support
close air support is exactly that
close to friendly forces and close to unfriendly forces
it requires a plane to be capable of absorbing a
great deal of damage as they come under fire
and to be incredibly accurate with its
weapons to avoid friendly fire
a plane with this role needs some unique qualities
it needs to be available at a moment's notice
in an ever evolving battlefield
troops could need support without warning
and because of this
the plane needs to be nearby and ready to go
this means working from forward bases that may not
necessarily have all the infrastructure and
equipment that other planes need to operate
its survivability needs to be best in class
flying this close to the ground is going to result in
every man with a weapon taking pot shots at the plane
as a result
the plane needs to be capable of dealing with small arms
machine guns
antiaircraft guns
and even missiles
ahtens frequently limp back to their base with damage so
severe that they would have downed another plane
with parts of their wings ripped off
with an engine taken out
and hydraulics on operational
and coming with this
the plane needs to be simple and cheap to manufacture
the air force made it clear from the beginning
in a battle of cost vs performance
cost would be prioritized
in an all out war with the Soviets
quantity and ease of manufacturing
was going to be a huge factor
like the Sherman and the t thirty four tanks
which were so influential in World War ii
a future war between the Soviets and the us
was expected to be won by whoever could out
manufacture and maintain their equipment
this plane was intended to be a cheap and rugged workhorse
it needed to be made with readily
available off the shelf parts
so maintenance crews could easily interchange
parts to repair damage quickly and at a low cost
contractors bidding for the manufacturing contract
needed to consider all of these factors and design
the entire plane around the primary ornament which
was chosen before the design process started
the general electric ga u eight a
a gun whose sound is so recognizable it has become a meme
the gun takes up a significant portion
of the plane's internal volume
at nearly six meters long
fitting snugly below the pilots
the largest part of the gun is the ammo drum
which typically holds one thousand one
hundred and fifty thirty millimeter rounds
the rounds are delivered to the seven
rotating barrels along a linkless shoot system
which also pulls the shell casings back into
the ammo drum after firing to prevent the
expended shells from damaging the plane
the belt system and the rotating cam firing system of
the barrels are both driven by a hydraulic motor
which is powered by two
independent hydraulic systems on board
there are two separate hydraulic systems
to ensure redundancy in operation
and both run the gun
the left and right hydraulic systems are pressurized by two
identical engine driven pumps on the left and right engine
if an engine is lost or one of
the hydraulic lines is broken
then the controls powered by
those hydraulics cease to work
however  the plane has been designed to allow it to
continue flying on only one hydraulic system
as both elevators
both ailerons and one rudder have hydraulic
power after loss of either hydraulic lines
ensuring powered control of pitch
roll and yaw even after the loss
of a single hydraulic system
if both are lost
the plane can switch to a manual
reversion flight control system
where the controls can be operated without power assist
which is difficult to say the least
but it can allow the pilots to land the plane safely
or at the very least allow them to
get into safe airspace to eject
this kind of redundancy can be found in every
component of the a ten to increase survivability
the landing gear is retracted by the left system only
but it can be extended by both
and in the event neither system is available
the wing mounted landing gear doesn't
actually retract all the way into the fairings
which allows the plane to land with landing gear
retracted with only moderate damage to the plane
protecting the control mechanisms through redundancy
is just one component of increasing survivability
the fuel tanks are self sealing on the lower portions
and are filled with foam to prevent explosions
the a ten like all planes can't fly with
significant armor covering every portion of the plane
so they just protect the most vital component on the plane
the stick operator
otherwise known as the pilot
who sits inside a Titanium tub
which is reported to be capable of absorbing direct hits
from Armor piercing rounds up to twenty three millimeters
the canopy is also made from ballistic glass
capable of taking hits from small arms
but this isn't the type of plane to be
flying upside down over the battlefield
this is more for shrapnel from
antiaircraft fire and missiles
the a ten also carries more chaff and flares
than any us air force legacy fighter
chaff is radar reflective material which
confuses radar controlled missiles
while flares confuse heat seeking missiles
with four dispensers located in the landing gear
pods and another four on the outer wing tips
for a total of sixteen across both wings
which can be triggered automatically by radar and
laser detection systems on the nose and wing tips of
the plane or simply fired manually by the pilots
one of the most striking features of the a ten is its
strange engine placement and tail configuration
and this too was a design feature to
thwart enemies with heat seeking missiles
the engines and tail were arranged like this to mask the
infrared signature of the hot exhaust of the plane
which could be used to lock onto the
plane by ir missiles on the ground
the tail would look more at home on a World War ii bomber
which were designed to be stable
stability was an important part of the a ten's design
the large vertical stabilizers help keep the plane
on target as it fires its insanely powerful gun
the gun is mounted directly on the centerline
of the plane to minimize the effect of the
recoil pushing the plane off target
the recoil force at forty four point five
kilonewtons is so powerful that it
effectively halves the plane's forward thrust
as each of the a ten's general electric t thirty four
engines produces just forty one kilonewtons of thrust
but the plane fires in such short bursts
typically one to two seconds that the pilot
doesn't need to worry about stalling
the high engines mounted behind the wings also reduced the
amount of dirt and dust that can enter the engines from
forward operating base runways which can be just dirt
runways  a lot of design choices were made to allow the
plane to operate from remote airfields like this
smaller military planes like this don't
typically have auxiliary power units
which are small secondary engines that
large planes like airliners have
you can see the exhaust of these little
hidden engines in the tails of airliners
these engines allow the plane to start its
main engines without external help
and help run functions like electricity
generation and hydraulic fluid pumps
but it's unnecessary weight for most small aircraft and they
usually use some other way to get the engine spinning
sometimes this results in the plane
relying on ground equipment
which the a ten cannot depend on
and so an apu was installed between the two podded engines
you can see the exhaust of the apu
just underneath the nacelles here
some of the most interesting design challenges
arose from the sheer power of the aircraft gun
the gun spits out so much burnt and unburned
propellant that they actually lost an early model in
nineteen seventy eight after exhaust gas from the
gun ignited and starved the engines of oxygen
to deal with this
some design changes were made
first  a small gas scoop was placed underneath the
barrels to suck in some of that exhaust
the chemical mixture of the round propellant was
changed to increase the flash suppressent levels
this in turn caused secondary problems as the new
chemical mixture caused residue to build up on the
cockpit windows and a canopy washer was needed
which simply sprayed the washing fluid onto the
canopy and the slipstream did the rest of the work
circuitry was also added to force the
engine ignition system to continually fire
while the gun trigger was being pulled
so that in the event a flameout occurred
the engine could reignite its flame immediately
the ga u eight avenger is a monstrous machine
designed to wreak havoc on those soviet tanks
attempting to push through allied lines
to do this  they need heavy armor piercing rounds
the rounds are truly massive at thirty millimeters
and sprinkled throughout these rounds are rounds
made of aluminum with a depleted uranium core
Uranium is insanely dense at nineteen
point one grams per centimeter cubed
lead in comparison is eleven point
three grams per centimeter cubed
and iron is seven point nine
this density gives the round more
Kinetic energy for Armor piercing
the depleted uranium also ablates material in
a way that self sharpens the projectile
while tungsten
which is slightly denser than uranium
tends to mushroom out and dulls itself upon impact
there is currently seven hundred thousand metric
tons of depleted uranium stored as uranium
hexafluoride in huge storage cylinders across America
costing uranium enrichment facilities
a great amount in maintenance
they are simply delighted when someone gets it
off their hands and fires it at high speed
into a country thousands of miles away
it's a cheap and freely available resource and has the
perfect material properties for Armor piercing
but the efficacy of using depleted
uranium is obviously not good
many war torn regions have blamed its
use for elevated cases of cancer
the a ten has been under constant threat of retirement
detractors have pushed from the very
start that the plane is not needed
first it was the f sixteen which should take
over its job and now it's the f thirty five
and both sides of the argument have valid points
the f sixteen and a ten can carry similar amounts
of ordnance into the battlefield if needed
both have eleven hard points with a
carrying capacity over seven point two tons
but attaching heavy equipments to its wings
negates the biggest advantage of the f sixteen
its maneuverability and ability to
conserve kinetic energy in dogfights
the f sixteen was designed to be a multi role fighter
while the a ten was designed for one job and one job only
getting down and dirty and taking some punches like rocky
while modern planes like the f thirty five
were designed to be more like Muhammad Ali  Bobbing
weaving  elusive
striking and moving out of the enemy's
range before they can react
the two planes were designed in completely different eras
with completely different military doctrine in mind and
trying to compare the two without acknowledging that is
silly
the f 35 is designed to carry a small payload of weapons